[
      {
         "question":"State how many bits in a byte.",
         "answer":"8",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "state"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "byte",
            "bits",
            "8 bits"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"State how many kilobytes (KiB) in 2 mebibytes (MiB).",
         "answer":"2048",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "state"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "kilobytes",
            "mebibytes",
            "KiB",
            "MiB",
            "conversion"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Identify unit equal to 4 bits.",
         "answer":"nibble",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "identify"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "4 bits",
            "unit",
            "nibble"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Define 16-bit colour depth.",
         "answer":"16 bits used to represent each colour in the image",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "define"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "colour depth",
            "16-bit",
            "definition"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give effect of changing resolution from 1000x1750 to 750x1500 on file size.",
         "answer":"The file size will decrease",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "resolution",
            "file size",
            "effect",
            "reduction"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Convert hexadecimal A2F to binary.",
         "answer":"One mark for each correct nibble, in the correct order.\n1010 0010 1111",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "conversion"
         ],
         "marks":3,
         "keywords":[
            "hexadecimal to binary",
            "A2F",
            "conversion"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Convert hexadecimal A2F to denary.",
         "answer":"2607",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "conversion"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "hexadecimal to denary",
            "A2F",
            "conversion"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Convert binary 000110011011 to hexadecimal.",
         "answer":"One mark for each correct character, in the correct order.\n1 9 B",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "conversion"
         ],
         "marks":3,
         "keywords":[
            "binary to hexadecimal",
            "conversion"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Convert binary 000110011011 to denary.",
         "answer":"411",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "conversion"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "binary to denary",
            "conversion"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give one reason addresses displayed in hexadecimal instead of binary.",
         "answer":"Any one from:\n• It is easier/quicker to read/understand/debug\n• It is a shorter representation of binary // It takes up less screen space",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "give reason"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "hexadecimal",
            "addresses",
            "advantages",
            "shorter"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Identify two other uses of hexadecimal in computer science.",
         "answer":"Any two from:\n• HTML colour codes\n• URL\n• Memory dump\n• IP address\n• MAC address\n• Assembly language\n• Error codes/messages\n• ASCII/Unicode",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "identify"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "hexadecimal",
            "uses",
            "colour codes",
            "error codes"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Calculate two's complement 8-bit integer for -25.",
         "answer":"One mark for correct working:\nExample: flip and add\nOne mark for correct answer.\n11100111",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"1 Data representation",
         "tags":[
            "two's complement"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "two's complement",
            "-25",
            "8-bit"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Complete table about secondary storage types.",
         "answer":"One mark for each correct type of storage.\ntype of secondary storage\noptical\nsolid-state\nmagnetic\nmagnetic\noptical",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "complete"
         ],
         "marks":6,
         "keywords":[
            "secondary storage",
            "optical",
            "solid-state",
            "magnetic",
            "types"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Identify correct statement about RAM.",
         "answer":"It stores data currently in use",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "multiple-choice"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "RAM",
            "characteristics",
            "currently in use"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"State characteristic making ROM primary storage.",
         "answer":"It is directly accessible by the CPU",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "state"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "ROM",
            "primary storage",
            "CPU accessible"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Circle three other input devices.",
         "answer":"touch screen\nmicrophone\nkeyboard",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "circle"
         ],
         "marks":3,
         "keywords":[
            "input devices",
            "touch screen",
            "microphone",
            "keyboard"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give two benefits of using sensors in automated system.",
         "answer":"Any two from:\n• Data can be collected without human intervention\n• Gathers data faster than a human\n• It will be accurate at taking readings\n• It can take readings continuously (24/7)\n• It can take readings in dangerous environments",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"6 Automated and emerging technologies",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "sensors",
            "automated system",
            "benefits",
            "monitoring",
            "response"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Complete table of sensor types and uses.",
         "answer":"One mark for each use (Max 1) per sensor:\nTemperature\n• Checking whether the water in a kettle is boiling\n• Monitoring the temperature in a room that is climate controlled\nHumidity\n• Checking whether the air is dry enough in a spray-painting garage\n• Checking whether the air is moist enough in a greenhouse\nInfra-red\n• Detecting motion in a room for a security system\n• Detecting whether a person is approaching automatic doors\nMagnetic field\n• Counting vehicles that cross a bridge\n• Monitoring vehicles that enter a car park",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"6 Automated and emerging technologies",
         "tags":[
            "complete"
         ],
         "marks":4,
         "keywords":[
            "sensors",
            "temperature",
            "humidity",
            "infra-red",
            "magnetic",
            "uses"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Explain serial half-duplex data transmission.",
         "answer":"One mark for each correct part of the diagram.\nThe diagram shows:\n• Bits beings sent one at a time\n• Bits being sent over a single wire\n• Data can be sent to and from the web server/network component/computers …\n• … not at the same time",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"2 Data transmission",
         "tags":[
            "explain"
         ],
         "marks":4,
         "keywords":[
            "serial half-duplex",
            "data transmission",
            "one direction at a time"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give two benefits of serial half-duplex.",
         "answer":"Any two from:\n• Bits will not be skewed // Bits are sent in order\n• Less chance of error\n• Less crosstalk/interference\n• Data can be sent over a long distance (if needed)\n• It is possible to download and upload data to the web server\n• Higher bandwidth than full duplex",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"2 Data transmission",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "serial half-duplex",
            "benefits",
            "cheaper",
            "two-way"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give one drawback of serial half-duplex.",
         "answer":"Any one from:\n• The transmission of data may be relatively slow\n• Data cannot be sent and received at the same time\n• May be more data collisions",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"2 Data transmission",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "serial half-duplex",
            "drawback",
            "slower"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give three cyber threats proxy server protects against.",
         "answer":"Any three from:\n• DDoS // DoS\n• Hacking\n• Malware // by example\n• Brute-force attack\nNOTE: three different examples of malware can be awarded.",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"5 The internet and its uses",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":3,
         "keywords":[
            "proxy server",
            "cyber threats",
            "DDoS",
            "malware",
            "unauthorized access"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Identify two functions of proxy server.",
         "answer":"Any two from:\n• Can limit the number of requests sent to the web server at a time\n• Can process common requests that will not need to enter the network\n• Act as a firewall\n• Examine incoming data to the webserver/network\n• Can have set rules/criteria for data to meet\n• Can have a blacklist/whitelist/list of IP addresses to block\n• Blocks traffic that doesn’t meet criteria\n• Closing certain ports",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"5 The internet and its uses",
         "tags":[
            "identify"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "proxy server",
            "functions",
            "caching",
            "filtering"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Describe how web pages are located, retrieved and displayed.",
         "answer":"Any six from:\n• The users type the URL into the address bar/web browser\n• The web browser sends the URL to the DNS\n• The DNS searches for the matching IP address\n• The DNS returns the IP address to the web browser\n• If the DNS cannot find the IP address it sends the URL to the next DNS\n• The web browser sends a request to the IP address/web server\n• The web server sends the data for the web page to the web browser\n• The web browser renders the HTML data to display the web page",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"5 The internet and its uses",
         "tags":[
            "describe"
         ],
         "marks":6,
         "keywords":[
            "web pages",
            "location",
            "retrieval",
            "display",
            "DNS",
            "HTML",
            "browser"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Describe CPU role in computer.",
         "answer":"To process instructions/data\nTo run the fetch–decode–execute cycle",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "describe"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "CPU",
            "role",
            "process instructions",
            "control"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"State purpose of register.",
         "answer":"Any one from:\n• To temporarily store data/instruction/address\n• To allow immediate access to data during the FDE cycle",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "state"
         ],
         "marks":1,
         "keywords":[
            "register",
            "purpose",
            "fast memory",
            "CPU"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give three registers built into CPU.",
         "answer":"Any three from:\n• Memory address register // MAR\n• Memory data register // MDR\n• Accumulator // ACC\n• Program counter // PC\n• Current instruction register // CIR",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":3,
         "keywords":[
            "registers",
            "CPU",
            "accumulator",
            "PC",
            "MAR"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Describe ALU purpose.",
         "answer":"Any three from:\n• To execute instructions\n• To perform calculations // by example\n• To perform logical operations // by example\n• To store interim results of calculations\n• Stores/reads/writes data to/from the accumulator",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "describe"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "ALU",
            "purpose",
            "arithmetic",
            "logic operations"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Explain why different CPU increases performance.",
         "answer":"Any Four from:\n• It could have more cores\n• … increasing the number of FDE cycles/instructions it can perform at the same time\n• It could have a higher clock speed\n• … increasing the number of FDE cycles/instructions per second it can perform\n• It could have a greater cache size\n• … meaning more frequently used data can be accessed faster",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"3 Hardware",
         "tags":[
            "explain"
         ],
         "marks":4,
         "keywords":[
            "CPU",
            "performance",
            "clock speed",
            "cores",
            "cache"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Complete paragraph about interrupt process.",
         "answer":"printer\ncomputer\npriority level\nfetch–decode–execute cycle\ninterrupt queue\nhigher\ninterrupt service routine (ISR)",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"4 Software",
         "tags":[
            "complete"
         ],
         "marks":7,
         "keywords":[
            "interrupt",
            "process",
            "priority",
            "FDE cycle",
            "ISR"
         ]
      },
      {
         "question":"Give two OS functions related to memory.",
         "answer":"Example:\n• Memory management\n• Multitasking",
         "paper":"S24P13",
         "topic":"4 Software",
         "tags":[
            "give"
         ],
         "marks":2,
         "keywords":[
            "operating system",
            "memory functions",
            "allocation",
            "virtual memory"
         ]
      }
   ]